<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-25T15:42:21+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mfX group</title><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Molecular physics of jumping nanodroplets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/06/drop-jump-nano.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Molecular physics of jumping nanodroplets" /><published>2020-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/06/drop-jump-nano</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/06/drop-jump-nano.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next-generation processor-chip cooling devices and self-cleaning surfaces can be enhanced by a passive process that requires little to no electrical input, through coalescence-induced nanodroplet jumping. Here, we describe the crucial impact thermal capillary waves and ambient gas rarefaction have on enhancing/limiting the jumping speeds of nanodroplets on low adhesion surfaces. By using high-fidelity non-equilibrium molecular dynamics simulations in conjunction with well-resolved volume-of-fluid continuum calculations, we are able to quantify the different dissipation mechanisms that govern nanodroplet jumping at length scales that are currently difficult to access experimentally. We find that interfacial thermal capillary waves contribute to a large statistical spread of nanodroplet jumping speeds that range from 0–30 m s^−1, where the typical jumping speeds of micro/millimeter sized droplets are only up to a few m s^−1. As the gas surrounding these liquid droplets is no longer in thermodynamic equilibrium, we also show how the reduced external drag leads to increased jumping speeds. This work demonstrates that, in the viscous-dominated regime, the Ohnesorge number and viscosity ratio between the two phases alone are not sufficient, but that the thermal fluctuation number (Th) and the Knudsen number (Kn) are both needed to recover the relevant molecular physics at nanoscales. Our results and analysis suggest that these dimensionless parameters would be relevant for many other free-surface flow processes and applications that operate at the nanoscale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="md" /><category term="rarefied" /><category term="fluctuations" /><category term="droplets" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-10-13-drop-jump-nano.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-10-13-drop-jump-nano.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coupling Molecular Dynamics and Direct Simulation Monte Carlo using a general and high-performance code coupling library</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/05/coupling-md-to-dsmc-comp-fluid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coupling Molecular Dynamics and Direct Simulation Monte Carlo using a general and high-performance code coupling library" /><published>2020-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/05/coupling-md-to-dsmc-comp-fluid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/10/05/coupling-md-to-dsmc-comp-fluid.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A domain-decomposed method to simultaneously couple the classical Molecular Dynamics (MD) and Direct Simulation Monte Carlo (DSMC) methods is proposed. This approach utilises the MPI-based general coupling library, the Multiscale Universal Interface. The method provides a direct coupling strategy and utilises two OpenFOAM based solvers, mdFoam+ and dsmcFoam+, enabling scenarios where both solvers assume one discrete particle is equal to one molecule or atom. The ultimate goal of this work is to enable complex multi-scale simulations involving micro, meso and macroscopic elements, as found with problems like evaporation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results are presented to show the fundamental capabilities of the method in terms of mass and kinetic energy conservation between simulation regions handled by the different solvers. We demonstrate the capability of the method by deploying onto a large supercomputing resource, with attention paid to the scalability for a canonical NVT ensemble (a constant number of atoms N, constant volume V and constant temperature T) of Argon atoms. The results show that the method performs as expected in terms of mass conservation and the solution is also shown to scale reasonably on a supercomputing resource, within the known performance limits of the coupled codes. The wider future of this work is also considered, with focus placed on the next steps to expand the capabilities of the methodology to allow for indirect coupling (where the coarse-graining capability of the DSMC method is used), as well as how this will then fit into a larger coupled framework to allow a complete micro-meso-macro approach to be tackled.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="mui" /><category term="dsmc" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-10-05-mui-coupling-comp-fluid.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-10-05-mui-coupling-comp-fluid.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/09/29/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2020-09-29T18:44:14+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-29T18:44:14+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/09/29/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/09/29/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&apos;Tom&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &apos;Hi, Tom&apos; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to new PhD students</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/09/01/yichong-and-abdullah-join-mfx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to new PhD students" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2020/09/01/yichong-and-abdullah-join-mfx</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/09/01/yichong-and-abdullah-join-mfx.html">&lt;p&gt;mfX welcomes two new PhD students, &lt;a href=&quot;/team/yichong-chen&quot;&gt;Yichong Chen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/team/abdullah-elrifai&quot;&gt;Abdullah El-Rifai&lt;/a&gt;, who will be working with &lt;a href=&quot;/team/matthew-borg&quot;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/team/rohit-pillai&quot;&gt;Rohit&lt;/a&gt;, respectively. Welcome Yichong and Abdullah!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><category term="group" /><summary type="html">mfX welcomes two new PhD students, Yichong Chen and Abdullah El-Rifai, who will be working with Matthew and Rohit, respectively. Welcome Yichong and Abdullah!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dense gas flow simulations in ultra-tight confinement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/09/01/dense-gas-pof.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dense gas flow simulations in ultra-tight confinement" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/09/01/dense-gas-pof</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/09/01/dense-gas-pof.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modeling dense gas flows inside channels with sections comparable to the diameter of gas molecules is essential in porous medium applica- tions, such as in non-conventional shale reservoir management and nanofluidic separation membranes. In this paper, we perform the first verification study of the Enskog equation by using particle simulation methods based on the same hard-sphere collisions dynamics. Our in- house Event-Driven Molecular Dynamics (EDMD) code and a pseudo-hard-sphere Molecular Dynamics (PHS-MD) solver are used to study force-driven Poiseuille flows in the limit of high gas densities and high confinements. Our results showed (a) very good agreement between EDMD, PHS-MD, and Enskog solutions across density, velocity, and temperature profiles for all the simulation conditions and (b) numerical evidence that deviations exist in the normalized mass flow rate vs Knudsen number curve compared to the standard curve without confine- ment. While we observe slight deviations in the Enskog density and velocity profiles from the MD when the reduced density is greater than 0.2, this limit is well above practical engineering applications, such as in shale gas. The key advantages of promoting the Enskog equation for upscaling flows in porous media lie in its ability to capture the non-equilibrium physics of tightly confined fluids while being computationally more efficient than fundamental simulation approaches, such as molecular dynamics and derivative solvers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="edmd" /><category term="md" /><category term="enskog" /><category term="gas" /><category term="confinement" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-09-01-dense-gas-pof.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-09-01-dense-gas-pof.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rarefied flow separation in microchannel with bends</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/08/28/bends-jfm.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rarefied flow separation in microchannel with bends" /><published>2020-08-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/08/28/bends-jfm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/08/28/bends-jfm.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on accurate numerical solution of the kinetic equation using well-resolved spatial and velocity grids, the separation of rarefied gas flow in a microchannel with double rectangular bends is investigated over a wide range of Knudsen and Reynolds numbers. Rarefaction effects are found to play different roles in flow separation (vortex formation) at the concave and convex corners. Flow separations near the concave and convex corners are only observed for a Knudsen number up to 0.04 and 0.01, respectively. With further increase of the Knudsen number, flow separation disappears. Due to the velocity slip at  the solid walls, the concave (convex) vortex is suppressed (enhanced), which leads to the late (early) onset of separation of rarefied gas flows with respect to the Reynolds number. The critical Reynolds numbers for the emergence of concave and convex vortices are found to be as low as 0.32x10−3 and 30.8, respectively. The slip velocity near the concave (convex) corner is found to increase (decrease) when the Knudsen number increases. An adverse pressure gradient appears near the concave corner for all the examined Knudsen numbers, while for the convex corner it only occurs when the Knudsen number is less than
0.1. Due to the secondary flow and adverse pressure gradient near the rectangular bends, the mass-flow-rate ratio between the bent and straight channels of the same length is a non-monotonic function of the Knudsen number. Our results clarify the diversified and often contradictory observations reported in the literature about flow-rate enhancement and vortex formation in bent microchannels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="md" /><category term="droplets" /><category term="vibrations" /><category term="wetting" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-08-28-bends-jfm.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-08-28-bends-jfm.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sreehari’s paper makes front cover!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/22/sreehari-paper-front-cover.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sreehari’s paper makes front cover!" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/22/sreehari-paper-front-cover</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/22/sreehari-paper-front-cover.html">&lt;p&gt;Sreehari’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1039/D0NR03766D&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on the molecular physics of jumping nanodroplets amade the front cover of &lt;em&gt; Nanoscale&lt;/em&gt;. Congratulations to [Sreehari] and [Matthew]!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><category term="publication" /><summary type="html">Sreehari’s paper on the molecular physics of jumping nanodroplets amade the front cover of Nanoscale. Congratulations to [Sreehari] and [Matthew]!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Enhanced nanoparticle rejection in aligned boron nitride nanotube membranes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/07/09/bnnt-nano.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enhanced nanoparticle rejection in aligned boron nitride nanotube membranes" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/07/09/bnnt-nano</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/07/09/bnnt-nano.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rejection of particles with different charges and sizes, ranging from a few Ångstroms to tens of nanometers,
is key to a wide range of industrial applications, from wastewater treatment to product purification
in biotech processes. Carbon nanotubes (CNTs) have long held the promise to revolutionize filtration,
with orders of magnitude higher fluxes compared to commercial membranes. CNTs, however, can only
reject particles and ions wider than their internal diameter. In this work, the fabrication of aligned boron
nitride nanotube (BNNT) membranes capable of rejecting nanoparticles smaller than their internal diameter
is reported for the first time. This is due to a mechanism of charge-based rejection in addition to
the size-based one, enabled by the BNNTs surface structure and chemistry and elucidated here using
high fidelity molecular dynamics and Brownian dynamics simulations. This results in ∼40% higher rejection
of the same particles by BNNT membranes than CNT ones with comparable nanotube diameter.
Furthermore, since permeance is proportional to the square of the nanotubes’ diameter, using BNNT
membranes with ∼30% larger nanotube diameter than a CNT membrane with comparable rejection
would result in up to 70% higher permeance. These results open the way to the design of more effective
nanotube membranes, capable of high particle rejection and, at the same time, high water permeance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="experiments" /><category term="md" /><category term="nanotubes" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-07-09-bnnt-nano.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-07-09-bnnt-nano.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Yonghao and Sina join mfX</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/01/yonghao-sina-join-mfx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yonghao and Sina join mfX" /><published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/01/yonghao-sina-join-mfx</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2020/07/01/yonghao-sina-join-mfx.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/yonghao-zhang&quot;&gt;Professor Yonghao Zhang&lt;/a&gt; has joined mfX as the inaugural Jason Reese Chair in Multiscale Fluid Mechanics, while &lt;a href=&quot;/team/sina-haeri&quot;&gt;Dr. Sina Haeri&lt;/a&gt; also joins as Lecturer. Welcome Yonghao and Sina!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><category term="group" /><summary type="html">Professor Yonghao Zhang has joined mfX as the inaugural Jason Reese Chair in Multiscale Fluid Mechanics, while Dr. Sina Haeri also joins as Lecturer. Welcome Yonghao and Sina!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/news/default-news.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Analysis of radiation pressure and aerodynamic forces acting on powder grains in powder-based additive manufacturing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/04/17/add-man-powder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analysis of radiation pressure and aerodynamic forces acting on powder grains in powder-based additive manufacturing" /><published>2020-04-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/04/17/add-man-powder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/2020/04/17/add-man-powder.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selection of process parameters is an important step in Powder-Based Additive Manufacturing (PBAM) of metals.Inorderto achieve an optimal parameterset,current literature ismainlyfocusedonthe understanding of powderdynamics by analysing the aerodynamic forces. In this letter, however, we show the importance of the laser in-duced force (radiation pressure) on the powder dynamics. Generalised Lorenz-Mie theory has been employedto accurately estimate the radiation pressure and it is shown that its magnitude is significant in comparison tovarious aerodynamic forces and the grains weight, hence, can significantly contribute to denudation and spatterobserved in the manufacturing process. Furthermore, the importance of compressibility and rarefaction effectson the magnitude of drag and lift forces that a particle experiences is demonstrated by estimating theMaandKnnumbers under process conditions, which directly impact the powder dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="mui" /><category term="dsmc" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-04-17-add-man-powder.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-04-17-add-man-powder.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>