<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-09T10:36:22+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mfX group</title><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Carlos’s recent paper highlighted by Physics of Fluids!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carlos’s recent paper highlighted by Physics of Fluids!" /><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/corral-carlos&quot;&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;’s recent paper in &lt;em&gt;Physics of Fluids&lt;/em&gt; has been higlighted as Editor’s pick! Congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;/team/corral-carlos&quot;&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;, and you can read his paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/5.0059712&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Carlos’s recent paper in Physics of Fluids has been higlighted as Editor’s pick! Congratulations to Carlos, and you can read his paper here.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Shaokang Li jons mfX as a PhD student!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shaokang Li jons mfX as a PhD student!" /><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX/">&lt;p&gt;Shaokang Li has joined mfX as a PhD student, to work with &lt;a href=&quot;/team/yonghao-zhang&quot;&gt;Professor Yonghao Zhang&lt;/a&gt;. Welcome Shaokang!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Shaokang Li has joined mfX as a PhD student, to work with Professor Yonghao Zhang. Welcome Shaokang!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is life? A perspective of the mathematical kinetic theory of active particles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is life? A perspective of the mathematical kinetic theory of active particles" /><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modeling of living systems composed of many interacting entities is treated in this paper with the aim of describing their collective behaviors. The mathematical approach is developed within the general framework of the kinetic theory of active particles. The presentation is in three parts. First, we derive the mathematical tools, subsequently, we show how the method can be applied to a number of case studies related to well defined living systems, and finally, we look ahead to research perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="mui" /><category term="dsmc" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract The modeling of living systems composed of many interacting entities is treated in this paper with the aim of describing their collective behaviors. The mathematical approach is developed within the general framework of the kinetic theory of active particles. The presentation is in three parts. First, we derive the mathematical tools, subsequently, we show how the method can be applied to a number of case studies related to well defined living systems, and finally, we look ahead to research perspectives.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-07-28-what-is-life.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-07-28-what-is-life.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Martin passes his viva!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/martin-viva/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martin passes his viva!" /><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/martin-viva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/martin-viva/">&lt;p&gt;Martin passed his PhD viva today with minor corrections! Congratulations are in order to &lt;strong&gt;Dr.&lt;/strong&gt; Martin Nikiforidis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Martin passed his PhD viva today with minor corrections! Congratulations are in order to Dr. Martin Nikiforidis.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/martin-viva.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/martin-viva.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Shock-induced collapse of surface nanobubbles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shock-induced collapse of surface nanobubbles" /><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of cavitation bubbles often releases high-speed liquid jets capable of surface damage, with applications in drug delivery, cancer treatment, and surface cleaning. Spherical cap-shaped surface nanobubbles have previously been found to exist on immersed substrates. Despite being known nucleation sites for cavitation, their collapsing dynamics are currently unexplored. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations to model the shock-induced collapse of different surface nanobubble sizes and contact angles. Comparisons are made with additional collapsing spherical nanobubble simulations near a substrate, to investigate the differences in their jet formation and resulting substrate pitting damage. Our main finding is that the pitting damage in the surface nanobubble simulations is greatly reduced, when compared to the spherical nanobubbles, which is primarily caused by the weaker jets formed during their collapse. Furthermore, the pit depths for surface nanobubble collapse do not depend on bubble size, unlike in the spherical nanobubble cases, but instead depend only on their contact angle. We also find a linear scaling relationship for all bubble cases between the final substrate damage and the peak pressure impulse at the impact centre, which can now be exploited to assess the relative damage in other computational studies of collapsing bubbles. We anticipate the more controlled surface-damage features produced by surface nanobubble cavitation jets will open up new applications in advanced manufacturing, medicine, and precision cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="nanobubble" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract The collapse of cavitation bubbles often releases high-speed liquid jets capable of surface damage, with applications in drug delivery, cancer treatment, and surface cleaning. Spherical cap-shaped surface nanobubbles have previously been found to exist on immersed substrates. Despite being known nucleation sites for cavitation, their collapsing dynamics are currently unexplored. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations to model the shock-induced collapse of different surface nanobubble sizes and contact angles. Comparisons are made with additional collapsing spherical nanobubble simulations near a substrate, to investigate the differences in their jet formation and resulting substrate pitting damage. Our main finding is that the pitting damage in the surface nanobubble simulations is greatly reduced, when compared to the spherical nanobubbles, which is primarily caused by the weaker jets formed during their collapse. Furthermore, the pit depths for surface nanobubble collapse do not depend on bubble size, unlike in the spherical nanobubble cases, but instead depend only on their contact angle. We also find a linear scaling relationship for all bubble cases between the final substrate damage and the peak pressure impulse at the impact centre, which can now be exploited to assess the relative damage in other computational studies of collapsing bubbles. We anticipate the more controlled surface-damage features produced by surface nanobubble cavitation jets will open up new applications in advanced manufacturing, medicine, and precision cleaning.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-07-02-bubble-collapse-sm.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-07-02-bubble-collapse-sm.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Saikat and Sreehari win prestigious fellowships!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saikat and Sreehari win prestigious fellowships!" /><published>2021-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/datta-saikat&quot;&gt;Saikat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/team/pd-sreehari&quot;&gt;Sreehari&lt;/a&gt; have both won Early Career Fellowships from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leverhulme.ac.uk/early-career-fellowships&quot;&gt;Leverhulme Trust&lt;/a&gt;! These prestigious fellowships are awarded across the sciences, arts, and the humanities. Huge congratulations to the duo!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Saikat and Sreehari have both won Early Career Fellowships from the Leverhulme Trust! These prestigious fellowships are awarded across the sciences, arts, and the humanities. Huge congratulations to the duo!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrick wins poster prize!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/patrick-poster-prize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrick wins poster prize!" /><published>2021-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/patrick-poster%20prize</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/patrick-poster-prize/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/sullivan-patrick&quot;&gt;Patrick&lt;/a&gt; won the &lt;em&gt;Best Poster&lt;/em&gt; prize at the School PGR conference today in a strong field of 200+ candidates! A well-deserved congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;/team/sullivan-patrick&quot;&gt;Patrick&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Patrick won the Best Poster prize at the School PGR conference today in a strong field of 200+ candidates! A well-deserved congratulations to Patrick!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/team/you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You?" /><published>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/team/you</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/team/you/">&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;/join-mfX&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn of ways to join our research group!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="team" /><summary type="html">Click here to learn of ways to join our research group!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/team/anonymous.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/team/anonymous.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Multiscale simulation of molecular gas flows by the general synthetic iterative scheme</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/poly-gsis-cmame/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiscale simulation of molecular gas flows by the general synthetic iterative scheme" /><published>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/poly-gsis-cmame</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/poly-gsis-cmame/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The in-depth knowledge of rarefied gas dynamics is crucial to address challenges in a wide range of engineering problems, where gas flows are usually multiscale, i.e., covering a wide range of Knudsen numbers. As the traditional Navier–Stokes equations fail, gas kinetic equations are required to model the flows. So far, very few numerical methods are designed to efficiently solve the multiscale gas dynamics and reveal the role of internal degrees of freedom of gas molecules. In this work, a general synthetic iterative scheme (GSIS) is proposed to find steady-state solutions of the gas kinetic equations for molecular gas flows accurately and efficiently, where the gas kinetic equations are solved together with the macroscopic synthetic equations that expedite solutions towards the steady state. In the macroscopic synthetic equations, while the momentum equation is the same as that used in the GSIS for monatomic gas, two energy equations are introduced here for polyatomic gases: one is for the translational energy and the other for the internal energy; these equations are derived exactly from the gas kinetic equations hence no approximation is made in final solutions. The Fourier stability analysis is performed to show that the GSIS permits fast convergence to steady-state solutions in the entire flow regime; meanwhile the asymptotic analysis shows that the GSIS recovers the Navier–Stokes equations when the Knudsen number is small, even on the spatial grid with cell size much larger than the molecular mean free path. With all these unique features, several challenging numerical examples are given to show that the proposed GSIS is a promising tool to simulate multiscale molecular gas flows and investigate the effects of internal degrees of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="GSIS" /><category term="polyatomic gas" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-01-01-poly-gsis-cmame.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2021-01-01-poly-gsis-cmame.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fast Convergence and Asymptotic Preserving of the General Synthetic Iterative Scheme</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/up-gsis-siam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fast Convergence and Asymptotic Preserving of the General Synthetic Iterative Scheme" /><published>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/up-gsis-siam</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/paper/up-gsis-siam/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently the general synthetic iteration scheme (GSIS) was proposed for the Boltzmann equation [W. Su et al., J. Comput. Phys., 407 (2020), 109245], where various numerical simulations have shown that (i) the steady-state solution can be found within dozens of iterations at any Knudsen number, and (ii) the solution is accurate even when the spatial cell size in the bulk region is much larger than the molecular mean free path, i.e., the Navier–Stokes solutions are recovered at coarse grids. The first property indicates that the error decay rate between two consecutive iterations decreases to zero along with $K$, while the second one implies that the GSIS asymptotically preserves the Navier–Stokes limit when the Knudsen number approaches zero. This paper is first dedicated to the rigorous proof of both properties. Second, several numerically challenging cases (especially the two-dimensional thermal edge flow) are used to further demonstrate the accuracy and efficiency of GSIS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="GSIS" /><category term="fast convergence" /><category term="asymptotic preserving" /><summary type="html">Abstract</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-12-14-up-gsis-siam.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/papers/2020-12-14-up-gsis-siam.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>