<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4002/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4002/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-17T15:56:50+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mfX group</title><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Giorgos joins mfX as a PDRA!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/giorgos-joins-mfx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giorgos joins mfX as a PDRA!" /><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/giorgos-joins-mfx</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/giorgos-joins-mfx/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/tatsios-giorgos&quot;&gt;Giorgos Tatsios&lt;/a&gt; has joined mfX as a PDRA, and will be working with &lt;a href=&quot;/team/matthew-borg&quot;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/team/livio-gibelli&quot;&gt;Livio&lt;/a&gt; on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://gow.epsrc.ukri.org/NGBOViewGrant.aspx?GrantRef=EP/V012002/1&quot;&gt;new EPSRC project&lt;/a&gt;. Welcome Giorgos!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Giorgos Tatsios has joined mfX as a PDRA, and will be working with Matthew and Livio on their new EPSRC project. Welcome Giorgos!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Carlos’s recent paper highlighted by Physics of Fluids!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carlos’s recent paper highlighted by Physics of Fluids!" /><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/carlos-paper-editors-pick/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/corral-carlos&quot;&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;’s recent paper in &lt;em&gt;Physics of Fluids&lt;/em&gt; has been higlighted as Editor’s pick! Congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;/team/corral-carlos&quot;&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;, and you can read his paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/5.0059712&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Carlos’s recent paper in Physics of Fluids has been higlighted as Editor’s pick! Congratulations to Carlos, and you can read his paper here.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Pore-scale gas flow simulations by the DSBGK and DVM methods</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-dsbgk-dvm-cf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pore-scale gas flow simulations by the DSBGK and DVM methods" /><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-dsbgk-dvm-cf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-dsbgk-dvm-cf/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shale gas flow at the pore scale is very challenging to simulate due to high Knudsen numbers (Kn), low speeds and complicated pore geometries. The direct simulation BGK (DSBGK) method and the discrete velocity method (DVM) are promising methods to simulate three-dimensional (3D) gas flows in the shale rock. As the grid-convergence accuracy and computational cost highly depend on the spatial and molecular velocity grids, here we present a rigorous study of the computational performance of the two methods by simulating gas flows through the standard 3D Sierpinski carpet. In this study, we found reasonable agreement between the DSBGK and DVM simulations when comparing the velocity profiles and permeability curves obtained by using fine spatial and velocity grids. However, the grid convergence of the DSBGK simulation is faster than that of the DVM, which requires a very large number of spatial and velocity grids for convergence. Consequently, the DSBGK simulation is orders of magnitude cheaper than the DVM simulation in terms of the CPU time and memory usage. While the DVM requires a high-performance computing facility to meet the memory demand of several hundreds of gigabyte for simulating this 3D flow problem, the DSBGK simulation can run on an ordinary laptop. This work therefore demonstrates the DSBGK method as a practical simulation tool for 3D pore-scale gas flows in the shale rock. Converged results generated in this study can be used as comparison data by other simulation methods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="porescale" /><category term="Sierpinski" /><category term="dsbgk" /><category term="dvm" /><summary type="html">Abstract Shale gas flow at the pore scale is very challenging to simulate due to high Knudsen numbers (Kn), low speeds and complicated pore geometries. The direct simulation BGK (DSBGK) method and the discrete velocity method (DVM) are promising methods to simulate three-dimensional (3D) gas flows in the shale rock. As the grid-convergence accuracy and computational cost highly depend on the spatial and molecular velocity grids, here we present a rigorous study of the computational performance of the two methods by simulating gas flows through the standard 3D Sierpinski carpet. In this study, we found reasonable agreement between the DSBGK and DVM simulations when comparing the velocity profiles and permeability curves obtained by using fine spatial and velocity grids. However, the grid convergence of the DSBGK simulation is faster than that of the DVM, which requires a very large number of spatial and velocity grids for convergence. Consequently, the DSBGK simulation is orders of magnitude cheaper than the DVM simulation in terms of the CPU time and memory usage. While the DVM requires a high-performance computing facility to meet the memory demand of several hundreds of gigabyte for simulating this 3D flow problem, the DSBGK simulation can run on an ordinary laptop. This work therefore demonstrates the DSBGK method as a practical simulation tool for 3D pore-scale gas flows in the shale rock. Converged results generated in this study can be used as comparison data by other simulation methods.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-08-15-pore-dsbgk-dvm-cf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-08-15-pore-dsbgk-dvm-cf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Shaokang Li jons mfX as a PhD student!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shaokang Li jons mfX as a PhD student!" /><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/shaokang-li-joins-mfX/">&lt;p&gt;Shaokang Li has joined mfX as a PhD student, to work with &lt;a href=&quot;/team/yonghao-zhang&quot;&gt;Professor Yonghao Zhang&lt;/a&gt;. Welcome Shaokang!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Shaokang Li has joined mfX as a PhD student, to work with Professor Yonghao Zhang. Welcome Shaokang!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is life? A perspective of the mathematical kinetic theory of active particles</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is life? A perspective of the mathematical kinetic theory of active particles" /><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/what-life-mathmodmethappls/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modeling of living systems composed of many interacting entities is treated in this paper with the aim of describing their collective behaviors. The mathematical approach is developed within the general framework of the kinetic theory of active particles. The presentation is in three parts. First, we derive the mathematical tools, subsequently, we show how the method can be applied to a number of case studies related to well defined living systems, and finally, we look ahead to research perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="mui" /><category term="dsmc" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract The modeling of living systems composed of many interacting entities is treated in this paper with the aim of describing their collective behaviors. The mathematical approach is developed within the general framework of the kinetic theory of active particles. The presentation is in three parts. First, we derive the mathematical tools, subsequently, we show how the method can be applied to a number of case studies related to well defined living systems, and finally, we look ahead to research perspectives.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-07-28-what-is-life.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-07-28-what-is-life.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Martin passes his viva!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/martin-viva/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martin passes his viva!" /><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/martin-viva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/martin-viva/">&lt;p&gt;Martin passed his PhD viva today with minor corrections! Congratulations are in order to &lt;strong&gt;Dr.&lt;/strong&gt; Martin Nikiforidis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Martin passed his PhD viva today with minor corrections! Congratulations are in order to Dr. Martin Nikiforidis.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/martin-viva.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/martin-viva.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Shock-induced collapse of surface nanobubbles</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shock-induced collapse of surface nanobubbles" /><published>2021-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/bubble-collapse-sm/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of cavitation bubbles often releases high-speed liquid jets capable of surface damage, with applications in drug delivery, cancer treatment, and surface cleaning. Spherical cap-shaped surface nanobubbles have previously been found to exist on immersed substrates. Despite being known nucleation sites for cavitation, their collapsing dynamics are currently unexplored. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations to model the shock-induced collapse of different surface nanobubble sizes and contact angles. Comparisons are made with additional collapsing spherical nanobubble simulations near a substrate, to investigate the differences in their jet formation and resulting substrate pitting damage. Our main finding is that the pitting damage in the surface nanobubble simulations is greatly reduced, when compared to the spherical nanobubbles, which is primarily caused by the weaker jets formed during their collapse. Furthermore, the pit depths for surface nanobubble collapse do not depend on bubble size, unlike in the spherical nanobubble cases, but instead depend only on their contact angle. We also find a linear scaling relationship for all bubble cases between the final substrate damage and the peak pressure impulse at the impact centre, which can now be exploited to assess the relative damage in other computational studies of collapsing bubbles. We anticipate the more controlled surface-damage features produced by surface nanobubble cavitation jets will open up new applications in advanced manufacturing, medicine, and precision cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="multiscale" /><category term="nanobubble" /><category term="md" /><summary type="html">Abstract The collapse of cavitation bubbles often releases high-speed liquid jets capable of surface damage, with applications in drug delivery, cancer treatment, and surface cleaning. Spherical cap-shaped surface nanobubbles have previously been found to exist on immersed substrates. Despite being known nucleation sites for cavitation, their collapsing dynamics are currently unexplored. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations to model the shock-induced collapse of different surface nanobubble sizes and contact angles. Comparisons are made with additional collapsing spherical nanobubble simulations near a substrate, to investigate the differences in their jet formation and resulting substrate pitting damage. Our main finding is that the pitting damage in the surface nanobubble simulations is greatly reduced, when compared to the spherical nanobubbles, which is primarily caused by the weaker jets formed during their collapse. Furthermore, the pit depths for surface nanobubble collapse do not depend on bubble size, unlike in the spherical nanobubble cases, but instead depend only on their contact angle. We also find a linear scaling relationship for all bubble cases between the final substrate damage and the peak pressure impulse at the impact centre, which can now be exploited to assess the relative damage in other computational studies of collapsing bubbles. We anticipate the more controlled surface-damage features produced by surface nanobubble cavitation jets will open up new applications in advanced manufacturing, medicine, and precision cleaning.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-07-02-bubble-collapse-sm.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-07-02-bubble-collapse-sm.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Saikat and Sreehari win prestigious fellowships!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saikat and Sreehari win prestigious fellowships!" /><published>2021-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/saikat-sreehari-Leverhulme-fellowship/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/datta-saikat&quot;&gt;Saikat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/team/pd-sreehari&quot;&gt;Sreehari&lt;/a&gt; have both won Early Career Fellowships from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leverhulme.ac.uk/early-career-fellowships&quot;&gt;Leverhulme Trust&lt;/a&gt;! These prestigious fellowships are awarded across the sciences, arts, and the humanities. Huge congratulations to the duo!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Saikat and Sreehari have both won Early Career Fellowships from the Leverhulme Trust! These prestigious fellowships are awarded across the sciences, arts, and the humanities. Huge congratulations to the duo!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Computational methods for pore-scale simulation of rarefied gas flow</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-methods-2D-cf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computational methods for pore-scale simulation of rarefied gas flow" /><published>2021-05-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-methods-2D-cf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/papers/paper/pore-methods-2D-cf/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct simulation at the pore-scale is crucial to unravel rarefaction effect on gas transport in tight porous media. To satisfy the dual demands on modeling accuracy and computation effort, an appropriate method must be chosen. This work, therefore, evaluates four numerical methods for pore-scale rarefied gas flows in a two-dimensional (2D) model porous media over a wide range of rarefaction. These methods are the incompressible Navier-Stokes equation with the first-order velocity-slip boundary condition, and three gas-kinetic solvers i.e. a finite-difference (FD) iterative solver for the linearized Bhatnagar, Gross and Crook (BGK) model kinetic equation, a finite-volume (FV) solver for the non-linear Shakhov model, and an open-source direct simulation Monte Carlos (DSMC) solver. The benchmark cases cover the characteristic Knudsen number ranging from 0.0231 to 4.62 while the characteristic Reynolds numbers are kept to be less than 1.0. All the solvers are developed in OpenFOAM, except the FD solver, allowing us to investigate the effect of local grid refinements using the automatic Cartesian grid generator in OpenFOAM. The flow fields and the apparent permeabilities predicted by all the solvers have been compared in detail. Besides, the computational time of these solvers is measured and analyzed to demonstrate the relative cost of the three kinetic solvers. It is found that the FD solver is the most efficient one and gives accurate results over the whole range of Knudsen number. Finally, this study also evaluates the feasibility of the recently developed discrete unified gas-kinetic scheme (DUGKS), the algorithm in the aforementioned non-linear Shakhov model equation solver, for pore-scale rarefied gas flow. It is found the results predicted by this solver agree well with the other two kinetic solvers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="paper" /><category term="porescale" /><category term="microflow" /><category term="Klinkenberg" /><summary type="html">Abstract Direct simulation at the pore-scale is crucial to unravel rarefaction effect on gas transport in tight porous media. To satisfy the dual demands on modeling accuracy and computation effort, an appropriate method must be chosen. This work, therefore, evaluates four numerical methods for pore-scale rarefied gas flows in a two-dimensional (2D) model porous media over a wide range of rarefaction. These methods are the incompressible Navier-Stokes equation with the first-order velocity-slip boundary condition, and three gas-kinetic solvers i.e. a finite-difference (FD) iterative solver for the linearized Bhatnagar, Gross and Crook (BGK) model kinetic equation, a finite-volume (FV) solver for the non-linear Shakhov model, and an open-source direct simulation Monte Carlos (DSMC) solver. The benchmark cases cover the characteristic Knudsen number ranging from 0.0231 to 4.62 while the characteristic Reynolds numbers are kept to be less than 1.0. All the solvers are developed in OpenFOAM, except the FD solver, allowing us to investigate the effect of local grid refinements using the automatic Cartesian grid generator in OpenFOAM. The flow fields and the apparent permeabilities predicted by all the solvers have been compared in detail. Besides, the computational time of these solvers is measured and analyzed to demonstrate the relative cost of the three kinetic solvers. It is found that the FD solver is the most efficient one and gives accurate results over the whole range of Knudsen number. Finally, this study also evaluates the feasibility of the recently developed discrete unified gas-kinetic scheme (DUGKS), the algorithm in the aforementioned non-linear Shakhov model equation solver, for pore-scale rarefied gas flow. It is found the results predicted by this solver agree well with the other two kinetic solvers.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-05-30-pore-methods-2D-cf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/papers/2021-05-30-pore-methods-2D-cf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrick wins poster prize!</title><link href="http://localhost:4002/news/patrick-poster-prize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrick wins poster prize!" /><published>2021-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4002/news/patrick-poster%20prize</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4002/news/patrick-poster-prize/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/team/sullivan-patrick&quot;&gt;Patrick&lt;/a&gt; won the &lt;em&gt;Best Poster&lt;/em&gt; prize at the School PGR conference today in a strong field of 200+ candidates! A well-deserved congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;/team/sullivan-patrick&quot;&gt;Patrick&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Multiscale Flow X</name><email>multiscaleflowx@gmail.com</email></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Patrick won the Best Poster prize at the School PGR conference today in a strong field of 200+ candidates! A well-deserved congratulations to Patrick!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4002/images/news/default.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>